Guide to the World War I Era Publications and Propaganda Codman Collection MS 055
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
World War I Era Publications and Propaganda
1898-1922
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Karolik, Martha Catherine Codman
MS 055
175
3 Linear Feet (7 Boxes)
A collection of U.S., U.K. and French publications primarily from the First World War and most are propagandistic in nature. The collection includes some ephemera and clippings from the era as well.
Provenance
The materials were collected by Martha Catherine Codman (Karolik) and obtained by Edward Dressler in an estate sale in Newport in the 1960s. Some materials belonged to Dressler and were likely interfiled with Codman-Karolik's materials.
Separated Materials
One newspaper clipping from 1854 and a Boston newspaper from 1903 were removed and placed with this repositories Miscellaneous Historic Newspaper collection. Additional clippings that had deteriorated to the point of being unreadable were discarded.
Related Materials
Similar materials may be found in this repository in the World War I Pamphlets and Bulletins Collection.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Scope and Contents
Materials in the collection show an active campaign to educate persons on military and political aspects of the First World War. Much of the material is designed to portray the war effort of the German and Central Powers in a negative light and the people (primarily the Belgians) as victims of German aggression. A common symbol is the barbarian Hun.
Primarily, the country of origin is used to designate the series breakdowns with an additional series made up of cartoons and another of postcards and miscellanea. Assuming that the material was all gathered in the U.S., much of the material from Great Britain may have been exported for sale in the U.S. or U.S. publishers may have reprinted materials.
The U.K. materials are divided by publication size as the size. This was done partially for ease of storage but it also demonstrates an aspect to the publishers' marketing of the material. Smaller publications generally have a one penny cover price (depending on the number of pages) and the tone of the material in many cases appears more provocative.
Most notable in the cartoon series is the book: Swollen Headed William which portays the Kaiser with a large swollen head.
Notable in the miscellanea series are two hand painted postcards, presumably from the First World War of Belgian man on horseback with his country's flag and another with a Russian man on horsebacke with his flag. In addition, in the collection's few non-WWI items, the series contains 3 volumes of the Russo-Japanese War Fully Illustrated published by Kinkodo Co., Tokyo.
Biographical / Historical
This collection was assembled by Martha Catherine Codman (1858-1948) whose great-great grandfather was Elias Haskett Derby of Salem, MA, sometimes called America's first millionaire. Codman split her time between, New York, Newport, RI and Washington, D.C.. In the 1920s, she married Maxim Karolik, a Russian-born opera singer with some controversy. Codman's philanthropic pursuits involved donations to various charities to benefit victims of the First World War. Likely as a result of her philanthropy, she accumulated literature regarding these charities as well as a number of published materials on the Allied war effort. Materials she collected included items published by the International Red Cross, Navy League, various Belgian relief charities, Committee on Public Information, etc. Newspaper articles show her making donations and on at least one occasion she hosted a concert at her home in Newport to aid orphans in France.
World War, 1914-1918 -- Pictorial works; World War, 1914-1918 -- Propaganda; Books; Booklets; United States -- History -- World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1914-1918 -- United States -- Periodicals; Maps.; Postcards; Publications.; Fliers (printed matter)
- U.S. Publications, 52730
  - Serials, 52773
    - Everybody's Magazine, Apr 1917; 52784 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      General note
      "The Spy Story of Belgium by Ian Hay
    - Independent, Jan 1917; 52783 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Codman mentioned on pg 16 - Lawrence of Arabia on cover.
    - Just Fun, Jun 1903; 52782 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Vol 1, #1
    - Liberty, 1935; 52781 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      July and August issues
    - Literay Digest, May 1918; 52780 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Judge (Judge's Library), 1898-1918; 52779 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      No. 114 Sep 1898 (Spanish American War - "Army Fun"); No. 148 Jul 1901 ("Strawberries"); No. 155 Feb 1902 ("Hi Holler"); No. 1936 Nov 1918 ("The Happy Medium")
    - Life, 1913-1919; 52778 (Box 1, Folder 7-24)
      4x fliers published by Life (1916?) entitled: "Germany's Latest Crime"
      Aug 21, 1913
      Dec 24, 1914
      Mar 9, 1916
      Mar 30, 1916
      April 13, 1916
      Jun 1, 1916
      Jun 22, 1916
      Sep 14, 1916
      Nov 2, 1916
      Oct 17, 1918
      Oct 31, 1918
      Nov 21, 1918
      Dec 5, 1918
      Dec 12, 1918
      Jan 16, 1919
      Jan 23, 1919
      May 15, 1919
    - New York Times "Supplements" - Rotogravure, Sep 1914-Nov 1914; 52777 (Folder OS 1)
    - Miscellaneous Clippings, 1914-1924; 52776 (Box OS 1, Folder 2)
      Regarding mobilization, the heads of the Soviet Union, and Lape/Bok Affair of 1924
    - Weekly Review (National Weekly), 1919; 52775 (Box OS 1, Folder 3)
      "Wilson in defeat"
    - Rreview of the conference on the limitation of armaments - in connection with the Pacific and Far East questions, 1921; 52774 (Box OS 1, Folder 3)
      Published by the Boston Evening Standard
  - Fundraising, 52753
    - Help Serbia: Save the women, children and old men from starvation by: Serbian Relief Committee. Publisher: Serbian Relief Committee., undated; 52772 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Refugees: Exhibition and sale of Mrs. Fiske Warren's collection of war posters and relics in aid of Belgian refugees, 1915; 52771 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Copley Hall, Boston
    - War Relief Clearing House for France and her allies: circular no. 3, 1915; 52770 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      15 Broad St, New York
    - French Flotilla Benefit, Jan 1916; 52769 (Box OS 1, Folder 4)
      2 Copies of the event program
    - Benefit Performance in aid of the Irish Wounded Publisher: The British War Relief Association, Inc.., May 1916; 52768 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Chandler Theater, New York
    - Souvenir Program: Ten Allies Costume Ball, Nov 1916; 52767 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Madison Square Garden, New York
    - American Charity in France by: Warren, Whitney., 1916; 52766 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Lecture given in Boston
    - First Annual Banquet, 1916; 52765 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      The New Willard, Washington D.C.
    - Gertrude Atherton in the war zone by: Atherton, Gertrude. Publisher: Le Bien-etre du Blesse., 1916; 52764 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Autographed
    - The Allied Bazaar: official program Publisher: National Allied Relief Committee., 1916; 52763 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Grand Central Palace, New York
    - The Army of the United States by: Young, Lt. Gn'l Samuel B.M.. Publisher: Michigan Commandery., 1916; 52762 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Military Order of the Loyal Legion of the United States
    - The outlook for international law by: Root, Elihu. Publisher: World Peace Foundation., 1916; 52761 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      40 Mt Vernon St. Boston
    - Ehibition of Paintings by M. Charles Duvent Publisher: American War Relief Work., Jan 1917; 52760 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      List and bw reproductions of selected works
    - Grand Benefit Publisher: Washington Committee of the American Fund for French Wounded., May 1917; 52759 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Belasco Theater
    - Americans of German origin and the war by: Kahn, Otto H.. Publisher: Merchants Association of New York at its Liberty Loan Meeting., Jun 1917; 52758 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Every American… should know all the facts in this folder Publisher: National Security League., Jun 1917; 52757 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      31 Pine St, New York
    - The Cartoon Book Publisher: Third Liberty Loan., ca.1917; 52756 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Art and artists Publisher: Committee on American Aid for the Restoration of Devastated Northern France through the French Ministry of Fine Arts., 1917; 52755 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Hero Land by: Rabajou, Capt.. Publisher: Management Committee., 1917; 52754 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      Christmas card with image of Rabajou's drawing and envelope. Gift in exchange for a "gift to the Allies." In the evelope was a pin labeled "Immunity Hero Land."
  - Navy League Publications, 52749
    - National Convention of the Navy League of the United States, booklets, Apr 1916; 52752 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      1. Program
      2. An adequate Naval Policy for the United States
      3. Essential Elements of foreign policy
      4. Manufacture and sale of munitions of war (x2)
      5. Navy personnel and the Reserve
      6. Our Purposes (x3)
      7. Political Benefits of Preparedness
      8. Safeguarding our inheritance (x2)
      9. Secretary's report
      10. The baneful influence of "politics" upon our foreign relations
      11. The defense of the nation as the business of the citizen (x3)
      12. The first step in national preparedness
      13. The Navy League, its founders and its work
      14. The rise and decline of the United States Navy in its relation to the international situation (x2)
      15. Why Congress is reluctant to develop the navy
      16. Why we need a navy general staff (x2)
    - Pamphlets, 1916; 52751 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      Nos. 45 and 82 - The American Navy as line of defense; Naval Strategy; 67 Reasons for a strong navy for defence
    - Women's Section, 1916; 52750 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      National service school of the Women's Section of the Navy League; Report of Elisabeth Ellicott Poe, General Secretary, Women's Section of the Navy League of the United States
  - U.S. Government, 52746
    - Congressional, 1917; 52748 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      Congressional Record - March 2, March 3; The Second Liberty Loan - address of W.G. McAdo
    - Committee on Public Information, 1917; 52747 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      "How War Came to America"; "The Government of Germany"
  - Miscellaneous Booklets and Fliers, 52731
    - League to Enforce Peace, 1915; 52745 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      William Howard Taft, President
    - World Court International Police. NY Bar Assn., Jan 1916; 52744 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Seaman, Louis Livingston, Maj., ca.1916; 52743 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      Aftermath of the Balkan War
      The Crucifixion of Belgium
    - The Story of French Officer Augustin Cochin, 1916; 52742 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Belgian deportations - Facsimiles, 1916; 52741 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - American Volunteer Motor Ambulance Corps report, 1916; 52740 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - George H. Doran published works, 1917; 52739 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      5 items:
      Peace: How to get it and keep it
      The dead lands of Europe
      The Zeebrugge Affair
      Turkey: a past and a future
      The Tanks (by request and with permission)
    - The Other side of the trenches - Lecture, Jan 1918; 52738 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      Carnegie Hall
    - The Tank, Dec 1918; 52737 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      British War Mission in the U.S.A.
    - Martyrdom of Belgium, undated; 52736 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - What about the secret treaties, undated; 52735 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Low, Maurice A. Publisher: Columbia Printing Co.., undated; 52734 (Box 2, Folder 35)
      3 items: Blockade and Contraband
      Great Britain's Share in the War
      The Law of Blockade
    - Austro-Magyar Judicial Crimes - Persecutions of the Jugoslavs by: Biankini, Ante., undated; 52733 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Testimony of an American Citizen in France by: Warren, Whitney., 1915; 52732 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- UK Publications, 52658
  - Miscellaneous Booklets and Fliers, 52668
    - "One Penny" (4.5 X 6"), 52702
      - Two Years of War by: Parker, Gilbert. Publisher: Burrup, Mathieson, & Sprague., 1916; 52729 (Box 3, Item 1)
      - What is England doing? by: Noyes, Alfred. Publisher: Burrup, Mathieson, & Sprague., 1916; 52728 (Box 3, Item 2)
      - Some facts about India by: Sloss, Robert. Publisher: Burrup, Mathieson, & Sprague., 1917; 52727 (Box 3, Item 3)
      - Russia and her allies Publisher: Burrup, Mathieson, & Sprague., 1917; 52726 (Box 3, Item 4)
      - British Staying Power by: Revelstoke, Lord. Publisher: Causton & Sons., 1916; 52725 (Box 3, Item 5)
      - Freedom of the Seas by: Balfour, Arthur J.. Publisher: Causton & Sons., 1916; 52724 (Box 3, Item 6)
      - Mercy Workers of the War by: Stanley, Authur. Publisher: Causton & Sons., 1916; 52723 (Box 3, Item 7)
      - Mails as a German war weapon Publisher: Eyre & Spottiswoode., 1916; 52722 (Box 3, Item 8)
      - Black List and Blockade by: Cecil, Robert. Publisher: Eyre & Spottiswoode., 1916; 52721 (Box 3, Item 9)
      - Naval prospects in 1917 by: Hurd, Archibald. Publisher: Eyre & Spottiswoode., 52720 (Box 3, Item 10)
      - Why Britain is in the War by: Grey, Viscout of Fallodon. Publisher: Fisher Unwin., 1916; 52719 (Box 3, Item 11)
      - Britain's case against Germany by: Gwatkin, H.M.. Publisher: Fisher Unwin., 1917; 52718 (Box 3, Item 12)
      - Workers' Resolve by: Appleton, W.A.. Publisher: Fisher Unwin., 1917; 52717 (Box 3, Item 13)
      - German truth and a matter of fact by: Robertson, J.M.. Publisher: Fisher Unwin., 1917; 52716 (Box 3, Item 14)
      - Great Britain's sea policy by: Murray, Gilbert. Publisher: Fisher Unwin., 1917; 52715 (Box 3, Item 15)
      - Horrors of Aleppo Publisher: Fisher Unwin., undated; 52714 (Box 3, Item 16)
      - Murder of Captain Fryatt Publisher: Hodder & Stoughton., 1916; 52713 (Box 3, Item 17)
      - British Finance and Prussian Militarism Publisher: Hodder & Stoughton., 1917; 52712 (Box 3, Item 18)
      - Slavery in Europe Publisher: Hodder & Stoughton., 1917; 52711 (Box 3, Item 19)
      - Murderous tyranny of the Turks Publisher: Hodder & Stoughton., 1917; 52710 (Box 3, Item 20)
      - Shirking the issue by: Archer, William. Publisher: Hodder & Stoughton., 1917; 52709 (Box 3, Item 21)
      - Germans and the small nations by: French, Lord. Publisher: J.J. Keliher., 1917; 52708 (Box 3, Item 22)
      - Russia: the psychology of a nation by: Vinogradoff, Paul. Publisher: Oxford University Press., 1914; 52707 (Box 3, Item 23)
      - Trade Control in War by: Donald, Robert. Publisher: Truscott & Sons., 1916; 52706 (Box 3, Item 24)
      - Why Mail Censorship is Vital to Britain by: De Bunsen, Maurice. Publisher: Truscott & Sons., 1916; 52705 (Box 3, Item 25)
      - Case of the Allies by: Balfour, James., 1917; 52704 (Box 3, Item 26)
      - Memorandum of the Belgian Government by: Dixon, W. Mcneile., undated; 52703 (Box 3, Item 27)
    - "Two Penny" and "Six Pence" (8.5 x 5"), 52680
      - Why Italy is with the Allies by: Hope, Anthony. Publisher: Clay & Sons., 1917; 52701 (Box 3, Item 28)
      - Character of the British empire by: Muir, Ramsay. Publisher: Constable and Co.., 1917; 52700 (Box 3, Item 29)
      - Six of one and half a dozen of the other by: Archer, William. Publisher: Fisher Unwin., 1917; 52699 (Box 3, Item 30)
      - England and her critics by: Borsa, Mario. Publisher: Fisher Unwin., 1917; 52698 (Box 3, Item 31)
      - Ireland and Poland by: Rolleston, T.W.. Publisher: Fisher Unwin., 1917; 52697 (Box 3, Item 32)
      - War on hospital ships Publisher: Fisher Unwin., 1917; 52696 (Box 3, Item 33)
      - Villain of the World-Tragedy by: Archer, William. Publisher: Fisher Unwin., undated; 52695 (Box 3, Item 34)
      - Belgian Deportations by: Toynbee, Arnold. Publisher: Fisher Unwin., undated; 52694 (Box 3, Item 35)
      - General Von Bissing's Testament Publisher: Fisher Unwin., undated; 52693 (Box 3, Item 36)
      - King of Hedjaz and Arab independence Publisher: Hayman, Christy & Lilly., 1917; 52692 (Box 3, Item 37)
      - League of Neutral States Publisher: Hayman, Christy & Lilly., undated; 52691 (Box 3, Item 38)
      - League of Peace and a free sea by: Corbett, Julian. Publisher: Hodder and Stoughton., 1917; 52690 (Box 3, Item 39)
      - Coming victory by: Smuts, General. Publisher: Hodder and Stoughton., 1917; 52689 (Box 3, Item 40)
      - British Commonwealth of Nations by: Smuts, General. Publisher: Hodder and Stoughton., 1917; 52688 (Box 3, Item 41)
      - True Pastime by: Gray, Alexander. Publisher: Methuen & Co.., 1917; 52687 (Box 3, Item 42)
      - Upright Sheaf by: Gray, Alexander. Publisher: Methuen & Co.., 1917; 52686 (Box 3, Item 43)
      - Turkish Prisoners in Egypt Publisher: Red Cross., 1917; 52685 (Box 3, Item 44)
      - When the War will end by: George, Lloyd., 1917; 52684 (Box 3, Item 45)
      - List of neutral ships sunk by the Germans, 1917; 52683 (Box 3, Item 46)
      - Those Gentlemen of Germany, undated; 52682 (Box 3, Item 47)
      - German attocities in France Publisher: Causton & Sons., 1916; 52681 (Box 3, Item 48)
    - (9.5 x 5"), 52673
      - Spectre of navalism by: Corbett, Julian. Publisher: Darling & Son., 1915; 52679 (Box 3, Item 49)
      - Eye-Witness at Louvain (x2) Publisher: Eyre & Spottiswoode., 1914; 52678 (Box 3, Item 50)
      - New German Empire Publisher: Hodder and Stoughton., 1917; 52677 (Box 3, Item 51)
      - Commemorative medal in the service of Germany by: Hill, G.F.. Publisher: Longmans, Green and Co.., 1917; 52676 (Box 3, Item 52)
      - Alleged German outrages Publisher: Macmillan., undated; 52675 (Box 3, Item 53)
      - Dishonoured army by: Morgan, J.H.. Publisher: Spottiswoode & Co.., 1915; 52674 (Box 3, Item 54)
    - (+8.5 x 11"), 52669
      - Belgium and Germany by: Davignon, Henri. Publisher: Thomas Nelson and Sons., undated; 52672 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Bernhardi Converted Publisher: Darling & Son., 1915; 52671 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Paliamentary publications, 1915-1916; 52670 (Box 4, Folder 3)
        Correspondence with the U.S. Embassador, Belgian Minister, reports and paper on German atrocities
  - Serials, 52659
    - The Sphere, 1914; 52667 (Box OS 1, Folder 5)
      2 issues from Aug 1914
    - Everyman, 1914; 52666 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      "The Lion of Belgium"
    - German Atrocities, 1915-1916; 52665 (Box OS 1, Folder 6)
    - Supplement to the London Gazette, Jul 1916; 52664 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - The Times History of the War, Jul 1915; 52663 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Illustrated London News - War Pictorial, Feb 1917; 52662 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - "The Crimes of Germany", undated; 52661 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      The Field - supplement
    - Scraps of Paper, 1916; 52660 (Box OS 1, Folder 6)
- French/Belgian Publications, 52652
  - Postcards, 1914-1916; 52657 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Journee Du Poilu (x8); "fallen hero of France" and envelope
  - La Belgique et Allemagne, 1915; 52656 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Inscribed by [Th]allon [M]asseige
  - Un Royaume en exil by: Ombiaux, Maurice des. Publisher: Le Pays de France., undated; 52655 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Nos. 1, 2, and 3. Regarding the King of Belgium in exile.
  - La Libre Belgique, Jul 1916; 52654 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    No. 83
  - Secour Americain et sympathies Americain by: Roz, Fermin. Publisher: Louis De Soye., Aug 1916; 52653 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Cartoons, 52646
  - Swollen-Headed William, 1914; 52651 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    General
    A parody of Der Struwwelpeter (1845) (or Shockheaded Peter) - a German children's book by Heinrich Hoffmann
  - Punch (U.K.), May 1916; 52650 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Cartoons Magazin (U.S.), Sep 1917; 52649 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - The Mad Dog by: Norton, Frederick., undated; 52648 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Will Dyson's Cartoon Book (U.K.), undated; 52647 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Postcards and Miscellanea, 52626
  - Postcards, 52635
    - Puzzle postcard of ship with envelope, undated; 52645 (Box 5, Folder Sleeve 1)
    - Alexandra (Lady) Colebrooke, undated; 52644 (Box 5, Folder Sleeve 2)
      3 postcards autographed by Colebrooke in various poses and costumes
    - Serbian, undated; 52643 (Box 5, Folder Sleeve 3)
      4 postcards documenting the situation in Serbia
    - Canada, undated; 52642 (Box 5, Folder Sleeve 4)
      4 postcards regarding the close bond between Great Britain and Canada
    - Misc. Color, undated; 52641 (Box 5, Folder Sleeve 5-6)
      8 postcards depicting Bruge, the branches of the British military, "Viva L'Italia, Shamrock Fund, Famous Liners, 21st Lancers, and "Fighting his battles over again"
    - Misc. B/W, undated; 52640 (Box 5, Folder Sleeve 7-9)
      10 postcards depicting tanks and other battlefield scenes
    - Cityscapes, undated; 52639 (Box 5, Folder Sleeve 10-12)
      10 postcards depicting Saint-Nazaire, London, Liverpool, and Brest
    - Red Cross, undated; 52638 (Box 5, Folder Sleeve 13)
      4 postcards (color) with envelope. Tuck's The "Red Cross" Series
    - The Allies (pre-1917), undated; 52637 (Box 5, Folder Sleeve 14)
      4 postcards (color) of flags and the group of allies' flags
    - Russia and Belgium, undated; 52636 (Box 5, Folder Sleeve 15)
      2 hand painted portraits. Both show horsemen holding the flag of their country in dress uniform. Ink and water color over a pencil sketch
  - Miscellanea, 52627
    - Russo-Japanese War Fully Illustrated Publisher: Kinkodo Co., Tokyo., 1904; 52634 (Box 6, Item 1-3)
      Nos. 2, 3, and 4
    - Verein Deutscher Eisenbahn-Verwaltungen Publisher: Association of German Railway Administrations., 1903; 52633 (Box OS 1, Folder 7)
      Zusammenstellbare Fahresheinhefte: Map of rail routes in Europe
    - Flag stickers and poster, undated; 52632 (Box OS 1, Folder 5)
    - The Service and its Insignia Publisher: Bailey, Banks & Biddle Co.., 1917; 52631 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      National Association for Universal Military Training
    - Official Crests of the Royal Navy Publisher: Gale and Polden., undated; 52630 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Official Crests of the British Army Publisher: Gale and Polden., undated; 52629 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Poster - German Colonial Possessions, undated; 52628 (Box OS 1, Folder 8)
      German colonial possessions surrendered to the allies since August 1914